Guide to the Asa Blair Papers
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
Asa Blair papers
1809-1848
MS 84
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
0.25
(1 box)
Pastor, Congregational Church, Kent, Connecticut. Chiefly letters to his wife during a trip to the South (1822) in which he describes Philadelphia, Baltimore, Washington, D. C. and Mount Vernon. A letter of Dec 2, 1822, describes the use of opium during his illness. Also in the collection are the correspondence of his wife Mira A. Blair and miscellaneous legal documents.
Blair, Asa, 1784-1823
Scope and Contents
The Reverend Asa Blair Papers consist primarily of letters he wrote to his wife, Mira Ann (Raymond) Blair, as he traveled in the United States seeking a climate to improve his health. Baltimore, Philadelphia and Washington, D.C. are among the cities Blair visited, and he commented extensively on both the locale and the inhabitants. In a letter of May 1, 1822, for example, he wrote "that Washington is behind no other place in wickedness-" Even some of the members of congress had stimulated too much to walk straight & swore like pirates." Blair also wrote of slavery and the lack of interest in religion in the Southern cities. Of special interest is his letter of December 2, 1822, in which he speaks of using opium to combat his illness.
Also included in the papers are letters to Mira (Raymond) Blair (1827-1848), and legal documents of Mira R. Blair and John Raymond, her father.
Biographical / Historical
Asa Blair, the second son of Captain Asa and Mehitable (Carnahan) Blair, of Blandford, Massachusetts, and grandson of Deacon Robert and Hannah (Thompson) Blair, of Western (now Warren) and Blandford, was born on May 12, 1784. He did not enter Yale until the Senior year. After graduation he studied theology with the Rev. Ebenezer Porter (Dartmouth Coll. 1791), of Washington, Connecticut, and was licensed to preach in 1811 by the Litchfield South Association of Ministers. On May 26, 1813, he was ordained and installed as pastor of the Congregational Church in Kent, in the immediate vicinity of Washington, where he exercised a useful ministry for about nine years. He received one hundred and seventy members to the church. Failing health led him on the approach of winter in 1822 to seek a Southern climate; and he died, on January 13, 1823, in Georgetown, South Carolina, in his 39th year, from typhus fever, after nineteen days' illness. He married Myra [sic] Ann, daughter of Dr. John Raymond, of Kent, who survived him with one son.
From Dexter's Biographical Sketches of the Graduates of Yale's College.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Opium abuse; Baltimore (Md.); Mount Vernon (Va.: Estate); Mount Vernon (Va.); Philadelphia (Pa.); United States -- Description and travel -- Early works to 1800; Washington (D.C.); Clergy; Blair, Asa, 1784-1823; Yale College (1718-1887). Class of 1810; Yale University -- Students
- Inventory
  - Letters written by Asa Blair to his wife Mira A. (Raymond) Blair, 1822 April-May (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Letters written by Asa Blair to his wife Mira A. (Raymond) Blair, 1882 November-Dec, undated (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Letter written by Asa Blair to William Blair [his brother] with biographical notes by Marion Brayton (Mrs. C. W.) Barrows, 1809, undated (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Letters written by Mira A. (Raymond) Blair, 1822-1823 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Letters to Mira A. (Raymond) Blair, 1827-1838 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Letters to Mira A. (Raymond) Blair, 1839-1844 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Letters to Mira A. (Raymond) Blair, 1847-1848 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Letter to John M. Raymond from William Watson, 1835 October 30 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Letter and legal documents concerning the death of Asa Blair, 1823 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Legal papers of John M. Raymond and Mira A. (Raymond) Blair, 1833-1843, undated (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Acknowledgment of Asa Blair's membership in the American Bible Society, ? May 30 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Receipt for John R. Blair's membership in the American Tract Society, 1832 April 23 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Lock of hair from John R. Blair, 1858 July (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - The Traveller's Directory Through the United States, by John Melish, 1822 (Box 1, Folder 13)